<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Peregrine — Game-centric detection worklist

  Product rule (non-negotiable):
    Only surface events that are meaningfully about the protected game process.
    No random system noise. No "any remote process" spam.

  Relevant event classes:
    EXTERNAL — action targets the game (target_pid ∈ protected game set)
    INTERNAL — anomaly inside the game process (caller/process == game)
               e.g. unbacked callstack, HWBP tamper, VAD private-exec, YARA, .text tamper

  Irrelevant (drop / never log as AC hit):
    - External ops to non-game PIDs
    - Self-access on non-game processes
    - Process-wide telemetry that is not game-scoped
    - Hooks firing without a game target (unless inject/hello for configured targets)

  Source of truth for "the game":
    Kernel: StateIsPidProtected (set by add_pid and auto StateAddPid on inject success)
    UI: protectedPids (must stay in sync)
    DLL: today has NO protected set — only "not self" (must fix)

  Environments:
    DEV  = edit/build only
    VM   = deploy + verify only place to mark done
    Status: todo | in_progress | done | blocked
-->
<todo>

  <feature name="game-centric-event-policy" priority="critical">
    <title>Game-only event policy (filter noise end-to-end)</title>
    <description>
      Enforce a single policy everywhere telemetry is produced or displayed:

        SHOW if:
          (1) EXTERNAL: target_pid is a protected game PID
              OR
          (2) INTERNAL: event occurs in a protected game PID
              (callstack anomaly, HWBP, image load noise rules, thread start outside modules, etc.)

        DROP otherwise.

      Kernel ObCallback and ETW UI already approximate (1).
      DLL IPC and UI handleIpcEvent currently use "not self" only — that is noise.
    </description>

    <task id="1" status="todo">
      <title>Document policy in README (short "Detection scope" section)</title>
      <description>
        State explicitly: Peregrine only cares about protected game PIDs (and AC self-defense).
        External = against game; Internal = inside game. Other processes ignored for AC logs.
      </description>
    </task>

    <task id="2" status="todo">
      <title>UI: filter all IPC external events on protectedPids</title>
      <description>
        File: src/peregrine-tauri/src/routes/+page.svelte — handleIpcEvent

        Today:
          targetProtected / callerProtected are computed but unused for RPM/WPM/OpenProcess/etc.
          Only !isSelf is checked → any remote target is logged.

        Required:
          - For external ops (OpenProcess, RPM/WPM, Virtual*Ex, CreateRemoteThread, …):
              log only if targetPID is in protectedPids (coerce number; handle string PIDs)
          - Optional: also allow if callerPID is game AND event is internal-class (usually N/A for those APIs)
          - CallstackAnomaly / HWBP / VehTableTamper / DebugRegister*:
              log only if callerPID (process hosting the DLL) is in protectedPids
              (internal signals only make sense in the game after inject)
          - hello: keep for inject targets (or only if pid becomes/is protected shortly after)
          - Never log external ops to non-protected PIDs

        Type note: IPC may send numbers; protectedPids is number[]. Use Number(target) consistently.
      </description>
      <acceptance>
        With game protected and cheat against game: external IPC lines appear.
        With DLL somehow observing open of notepad PID: no AC log line.
      </acceptance>
    </task>

    <task id="3" status="todo">
      <title>UI: audit driver-event and ETW paths for game scope</title>
      <description>
        Confirm / fix:
        - ETW: already drops if target not in protectedPids — keep; ensure caller==target drop stays
        - ob_callback: kernel already filters; UI may still show only dangerous — OK
        - thread_create / image_load: only emitted for protected PIDs in kernel — OK
        - file_access: AC self-defense, not game — keep as separate "AC defense" tag (allowed noise class)
        - system_check / driver_scan / hwid: machine-level, not per-game — keep as ops/admin, not cheat hits
          (optional: separate log filter tabs later; not required now)

        Do not start logging process_create system-wide.
      </description>
    </task>

    <task id="4" status="todo">
      <title>DLL: optional protected-PID awareness (preferred over UI-only filter)</title>
      <description>
        Goal: do not even send noisy IPC JSON for non-game targets (less pipe spam, less forge surface).

        Design (pick one robust approach — no hacks):
        A) Kernel IOCTL / shared section: list of protected PIDs readable by injected DLL
        B) After hello, GUI writes protected set to DLL via named pipe command (DLL needs read path)
        C) DLL only injected into game: then "internal" is always game; external from game is rare —
           still filter target==self for internal-only tools; for external from another injected
           process you still need A/B

        Recommended for AC:
        - Primary inject = game only → internal events always game-scoped
        - External detection relies on ObCallback + ETW (already game-scoped) more than on
          cheat-process injection
        - If we inject into cheats later, require protected-PID list in DLL before logging external

        Minimum for this task if inject-only-into-game:
        - Document that external-against-game is ObCallback/ETW primary
        - DLL internal events (callstack/HWBP) always imply current process is game after inject
        - UI still filters IPC external with protectedPids (task 2) as safety net

        If implementing A/B: log external only when targetPID ∈ protected set inside dllmain hooks.
      </description>
    </task>

    <task id="5" status="todo">
      <title>RPM/WPM hooks: do not log every remote; require game target</title>
      <description>
        dllmain.cpp currently logs all NtR/NtW/RPM/WPM with targetPID without checking game set.
        After task 2/4: either UI drops non-game, or DLL never sends.

        Also consider: self RPM inside game is usually not interesting — drop isSelf for AC log
        (keep callstack_check if useful for internal shellcode calling RPM on self — rare).

        Double-report KernelBase+Nt*: if both fire for same op to game, dedupe or only hook ntdll
        for R/W to cut noise (game-related still, just once).
      </description>
    </task>
  </feature>

  <feature name="ntdll-coverage-game-scoped" priority="high" depends-on="game-centric-event-policy">
    <title>Expand ntdll hooks only for game-relevant external ops</title>
    <description>
      We already hook NtRead/WriteVirtualMemory + NtSetContextThread and KernelBase Open/Alloc/CRT.
      Gap: NtOpenProcess / NtAllocateVirtualMemory / NtProtectVirtualMemory / NtCreateThreadEx
      bypass KernelBase hooks.

      Only add hooks that can be filtered to (target == game) or (internal in game).
      Do not add broad "log every Nt*" noise.
    </description>

    <task id="10" status="todo">
      <title>Add game-filterable ntdll hooks</title>
      <description>
        In PeregrineDLL dllmain (MinHook on ntdll):
        - NtOpenProcess — log only if ClientId.UniqueProcess is protected game (needs PID set or UI filter)
        - NtAllocateVirtualMemory — if ProcessHandle resolves to game PID and not self (or self+RX suspicious later)
        - NtProtectVirtualMemory — same
        - NtCreateThreadEx — same (remote into game)

        Optional later (still game-scoped):
        - NtOpenThread — only if thread's process is game
        - NtQueueApcThread(Ex) — target thread in game
        - NtMapViewOfSection — section mapped into game

        Keep KernelBase hooks or drop duplicates once ntdll path is solid (prefer one layer for R/W already ntdll).
      </description>
    </task>

    <task id="11" status="todo">
      <title>Callstack_check only for game-scoped hook fires</title>
      <description>
        Rate limits (2/min on RPM) already drop signal. After game filter, fewer fires —
        raise limits slightly for game-targeted ops only so real cheats still produce CallstackAnomaly.
        Do not raise global limits for unfiltered traffic (there should be no unfiltered traffic).
      </description>
    </task>
  </feature>

  <feature name="test-suite-game-scope" priority="high" depends-on="game-centric-event-policy">
    <title>Extend test/ tools so VM verification proves game-only filtering</title>
    <description>
      Existing cheats (cheat.exe, cheat_inject, shellcode, …) already take game PID — good for
      positive tests (expect events when targeting game).

      Missing: negative tests (ops against non-game must produce NO AC hit) and a short matrix
      in README or test/README.
    </description>

    <task id="20" status="todo">
      <title>Positive matrix (document + run on VM)</title>
      <description>
        With injection target = game.exe, connect GUI, let inject + auto-protect:

        | Test | Expect |
        |------|--------|
        | cheat.exe &lt;game_pid&gt; &lt;addr&gt; | ObCallback and/or ETW and/or IPC external → game |
        | cheat_inject / shellcode / manualmap / patch / yara / callstack / hwbp | existing detections, all game-scoped |
        | Module check / VAD / threads on game PID | findings only for that PID |

        Record which sensor fired (ObCallback vs IPC vs ETW) so we know primary path.
      </description>
    </task>

    <task id="21" status="todo">
      <title>Negative test: external ops against non-game PID</title>
      <description>
        New tool e.g. test/cheat_noise.c (or flag on cheat.exe):
        - OpenProcess + RPM against a benign PID (e.g. current process of another helper,
          or notepad started for the test) — NOT the game
        - Optionally also VirtualAllocEx remote on non-game

        Expect after filter work:
        - NO [External …] IPC lines for that activity in AC log
        - NO ETW-TI lines (target not protected)
        - NO ob_callback for that target

        Optional: start notepad, run noise cheat, confirm log stays clean while game remains protected.
      </description>
    </task>

    <task id="22" status="todo">
      <title>Negative test: activity inside non-game process with no inject</title>
      <description>
        Run a process that allocates RWX / calls OpenProcess on itself without being game or inject target.
        Expect: no Peregrine AC cheat hits (no hello, no callstack from our DLL).
      </description>
    </task>

    <task id="23" status="todo">
      <title>Positive: internal-only in game still visible</title>
      <description>
        After inject into game:
        - cheat_callstack / cheat_hwbp targeting game must still show CallstackAnomaly / HWBP events
        - These are INTERNAL (process == game); must not be dropped by "external target" filter
        - UI rule: callerPID ∈ protectedPids for internal event types
      </description>
    </task>

    <task id="24" status="todo">
      <title>test/README.md or README Test Suite section: game-scope matrix</title>
      <description>
        Document positive/negative cases and how to run on VM.
        Explicit pass criteria: zero AC log spam when noise cheat runs against non-game.
      </description>
    </task>

    <task id="25" status="todo">
      <title>build.bat: include new noise test binary</title>
      <description>
        Wire cheat_noise.exe (or equivalent) into test/build.bat.
      </description>
    </task>
  </feature>

  <feature name="optional-followups" priority="low">
    <title>Later — only if still game-scoped</title>
    <task id="30" status="todo" optional="true">
      <title>Thread ObCallbacks report-only for handles to game threads</title>
      <description>
        Same filter: only when thread belongs to protected process. No system-wide thread noise.
      </description>
    </task>
    <task id="31" status="todo" optional="true">
      <title>Continuous scans only against protected PIDs</title>
      <description>
        Timer: integrity/VAD/threads/YARA for each pid in protected set — never full system walk for AC hits.
      </description>
    </task>
    <task id="32" status="todo" optional="true">
      <title>ObCallback strip (enforcement) after report path is clean</title>
      <description>
        Protect, not detection — only after game-scoped reporting is trusted.
      </description>
    </task>
  </feature>

  <workflow>
    <recommended_order>
      1 → 2 → 3 → 5 → 20 → 21 → 23 → 24 → 25 → 4 → 10 → 11 → 22 → 30…
    </recommended_order>
    <rationale>
      Filter first (UI + policy), then prove with negative/positive tests, then expand ntdll
      hooks under the same filter. Do not add hooks before game-only filtering lands.
    </rationale>
    <rules>
      <rule>If an event cannot be attributed to a protected game PID (as target or host), it must not appear as a cheat/AC detection log line.</rule>
      <rule>Machine-level ops (driver scan, system check, HWID, file self-defense) stay separate — never mixed into "cheat against game" semantics.</rule>
      <rule>No hacks: prefer shared protected-PID source of truth over brittle string matching of process names in the DLL.</rule>
      <rule>Expand tests whenever a new filter or hook is added; negative tests are mandatory for filter work.</rule>
      <rule>Verify only on the dedicated Windows VM; mark done only after positive + negative cases pass.</rule>
    </rules>
    <build>
      <item>DEV: rebuild DLL / GUI / test tools as needed</item>
      <item>VM: deploy, inject game.exe, run positive cheats + noise against non-game, confirm log policy</item>
    </build>
  </workflow>

</todo>
